<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<GameData>
  <LocalizedText>
    <Row Tag="LOC_CIVILIZATION_MONGOLIA_NAME" Language="en_US">
		<Text>Mongolia</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="LOC_LEADER_GENGHIS_KHAN_NAME" Language="en_US">
		<Text>Genghis Khan</Text>
    </Row>
	<Row Tag="LOC_TRAIT_CIVILIZATION_MONGOL_TERROR_NAME" Language="en_US">
		<Text>Mongol Terror</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="LOC_TRAIT_CIVILIZATION_MONGOL_TERROR_DESCRIPTION" Language="en_US">
		<Text>+7 [ICON_Strength] for all units when fighting city states.</Text>
    </Row>
	<Row Tag="LOC_UNIT_KESHIK_NAME" Language="en_US">
		<Text>Keshik</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="LOC_UNIT_KESHIK_DESCRIPTION" Language="en_US">
		<Text>The Mongol unique ranged mounted unit. Replaces the Knight with slightly less [ICON_Strength] but 1 extra movement and the ability to move after attacking.</Text>
    </Row>
	<Row Tag="LOC_UNIT_KHAN_NAME" Language="en_US">
		<Text>Khan</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="LOC_UNIT_KHAN_DESCRIPTION" Language="en_US">
		<Text>The Mongol unique support unit. Provides 7 extra healing per turn, enables full wall damage, and provides 4 [ICON_Strength] strength to all adjacent units.</Text>
    </Row>
	<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_KESHIK_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1" Language="en_US">
		<Text>In the 13th century the Mongols came boiling out of Central Asia, conquering most of Asia, Eastern Europe and a large portion of the Middle East by the end of the century. The Mongols' primary weapon was their incomparable horse archers, the Keshiks. The Mongols were nomadic tribesmen, and their children were almost literally "raised in the saddle." Riding on their small but hearty steppe ponies, the lightly-armed and armored Mongols could cover an astonishing amount of territory in a day, far outpacing any infantry or even the heavier European cavalry. In battle the Mongol Keshiks would shoot from horseback with deadly accuracy, disrupting and demoralizing the enemy formations. Once the enemy was suitably weakened, the Mongol heavy cavalry units would charge into the wavering foe to deliver the coup de grace. When facing armored European knights the Mongols would simply shoot their horses, then ignore or destroy the unhorsed men as they wished.</Text>
	</Row>
    <Row Tag="LOC_TRAIT_LEADER_THREATENING_IMPRESSION_NAME" Language="en_US">
		<Text>Threatening Impression</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="LOC_TRAIT_LEADER_THREATENING_IMPRESSION_DESCRIPTION" Language="en_US">
		<Text>Can levy the military of allied city states at a 10% discount.</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="LOC_CIVILIZATION_MONGOLIA_DESCRIPTION" Language="en_US">
		<Text>Mongol Empire</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="LOC_LOADING_INFO_LEADER_GENGHIS_KHAN" Language="en_US">
		<Text>Greetings o great Temüjin, immortal emperor of the mighty Mongol Empire! Your fists shatter walls of cities and your voice brings despair to your enemies. O Khan! you united the warring tribes of Northern Asia into a mighty people, creating the greatest cavalry force the world has ever witnessed. Your people's cunning diplomacy divided their enemies, making them weak and helpless before Mongolia's conquering armies. In a few short years, your soldiers conquered most of China and Eastern Asia, and the empire continued to grow until it reached west into Europe and south to Korea. Indeed, it was the greatest empire ever seen, dwarfing those pathetic conquests of the Romans or the Greeks. Temüjin, your people call upon you once more to lead them to battle and conquest. Will the world once again tremble at the thunderous sound of your cavalry, sweeping down from the steppes? Will you build an empire that stands the test of time?</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GENGHIS_KHAN_TITLE" Language="en_US">
		<Text>Temüjin</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GENGHIS_KHAN_SUBTITLE" Language="en_US">
		<Text>Khan</Text>
    </Row>			
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_GENGHIS_KHAN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1" Language="en_US">
		<Text>Genghis Khan is one of the most recognized and most feared leaders in all of human history. Hundreds of statues, buildings, and commercial products bear his image, and numerous entertainment works have been created honoring his life. He became the first to unite the warring, nomadic tribes of northeast Asia and founded the largest contiguous empire known to man. Perhaps less known are the improvements and advancements he made in infrastructure, trade, and religious tolerance. More than just a warrior, he was also a capable and shrewd civil leader. Born Borjigin Temüjin in 1162 AD, Temüjin was raised in a Mongol tribe that inhabited the lands near modern-day Ulaanbaatar. The third oldest son of a tribal chieftain, he is said to be named after a captured Tatar chieftain. Much of Temüjin's early life is shrouded in mystery, and the few sources which do exist often conflict and disagree. No accurate portraits or pictures of him exist today, but many sources describe Temüjin as a "glittering" man, sporting long red hair and blue-green eyes. Like many of the tribesmen in the region Temüjin's early life was pretty difficult, despite being born into nobility. At the age of nine he was betrothed to a neighboring tribe-chieftain's daughter and sent to live with her family. His father was killed on the way back home, and Temüjin's tribe subsequently abandoned him and the remainder of his family. The family lived destitute until he married his betrothed at the age of 16. Temüjin began his bid for power by offering himself as a vassal to his late father's blood brother, Toghrul, the Khan of the Kerait tribe. During this time, Temüjin's wife was captured by the Merkit tribe, and Toghrul lent the young warlord 20,000 men to face them in battle. Not only did Temüjin recapture his wife, but he also completely defeated the Merkits, bringing them under this control. He became a Khan in his own right and began conquering more of the neighboring tribes. During his conquests the young Khan fundamentally broke with Mongol tradition - he created a new set of laws and incorporated his captured holdings into his growing empire, rather than destroying and pillaging them. His law, the Yassa, promised soldiers fair pay and wealth, outlawed thievery and pillaging of any kind, and promised protection and religious freedom for all conquered tribes. Temüjin's political innovations brought him much loyalty and strongly united his growing nation. The rest of his outward expansion and unification of the Mongol tribes is filled with tales of betrayal, intrigue, dashing victories, conspiracies, familial disputes, and more betrayal, including rifts between his former ally Toghrul and eldest son Jochi. However, despite these setbacks he managed to subdue or unite all the nomadic tribes in the Mongolia area by 1206, the first man to ever do so. At a joint council of chiefs he was given the name "Genghis Khan," the eternal and universal ruler of the Mongol peoples. After the unification of Mongolia, Genghis soon began a series of successful military campaigns to conquer the surrounding and outlying areas, creating a massive empire under his rule. In 1209, he forced the surrender of the Xia provinces, and shortly thereafter in 1211, he finished the conquest of the Jin Dynasty. Next he turned his attention west toward Persia. In a deft maneuver containing only two armies of 20,000 men each, Genghis launched a successful attack against the Kara-Khitan Khanate, putting his reach of control right on Persia's doorstep. Rather than conquer the neighboring empire of Khwarezmia, Genghis instead offered a political alliance, sending a 500-man trade caravan to the capital - he hoped to create a powerful trading partner using the Silk Road. However, the Khwarezmian Shah distrusted the young leader and slaughtered the caravan. Trying once more, Genghis sent a group of ambassadors to the Shah directly, who answered the gesture by beheading one of them. Outraged, Genghis assembled some 200,000 men and personally oversaw the bloody fall and abject subjugation of the Khwarezmian Empire in 1220. Immediately following his success he captured many other regions on his way back to Mongolia, including Georgia, Afghanistan, and the remaining Western Xia holdings. His victorious journey complete, Genghis's empire now stretched from the Caspian Sea in the west all the way to the Sea of Japan in the east, twice the size of the Roman Empire. Now an aged man, the topic of Genghis's succession was heated and highly contested. His eldest son, Jochi, was suspected of being born of a different man (as a result of his wife's capture), and many refused outright to follow him. The clash ended however in 1226 when Jochi died mysteriously, some claiming that Genghis himself ordered the boy poisoned. His middle son Ogedei was named heir, as Genghis thought him the most level headed and stable of his remaining children. Shortly after in 1227 Genghis died, the reason for which is still debated. Some claim he fell from his horse during a battle against the Tangut people, others hold that he was struck down by a long illness. Some even claim that a captured Tangut princess killed him with a pair of pliers. Regardless of the means or reason, Genghis Khan was buried in an unmarked grave as he wished, its location a closely guarded family secret. Some folklore claims that a river was diverted over the site to protect it; other stories describe a grove of trees planted atop the grave to hide it. In 2004, an archaeological dig uncovered what is believed to be the ruins of Genghis' palace. Hope remains that his grave may yet be found. Depending on whom you ask, Genghis Khan is regarded as a worthy leader and excellent ruler or, conversely as a bloodthirsty killer. In present-day Mongolia, he is thought of favorably as the father of the nation, and his many political innovations are upheld and heralded. In formerly conquered lands, such as Iraq and Iran, he is seen almost universally as a genocidal, maniacal tyrant who caused untold destruction and damage. Whether his tales of greatness or brutality are contested or exaggerated, he is undoubtedly one of the most important and influential leaders in the ancient world, his legacy still remaining strong and visible even today.</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_MONGOLIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1" Language="en_US">
		<Text>The Mongolian Empire formed the largest contiguous empire in the history of the world, stretching from the Danube to the Sea of Japan and from Siberia to Cambodia - roughly 22% of the Earth's land area. From humble beginnings as a mish-mash of unaligned nomadic tribes, the Mongols changed the face of the ancient world and became one of the most feared and effective military forces ever to walk the land. Spreading across eastern Asia, Mongolia's geography is rugged and varied, with steep mountain ranges in the north and west, verdant steppes throughout the central part of the country, and the Gobi Desert bordering on the south. While the steppes could serve as bountiful pasture land, Mongolia's harsh climate dictates otherwise. Summers are short and hot, while the long, frigid winters cover the country in devastating blizzards (known as zud), making grazing all but impossible for large parts of the year. Temperatures as low as -30 C (-22 F) during the winter are not uncommon. From at least Paleolithic times, nomadic tribes have dominated the Mongolian landscape. These tribes were adept farmers as well as huntsmen, only staying on the move to keep ahead of the harsh winters and dry summers. They were skilled horsemen and archers, particularly accomplished in mounted combat. Occasionally, some individual tribes formed confederations, such as the Xiongnu alliance in 209 BC. While threatening enough en masse to force the Qin Dynasty to construct the Great Wall of China, these loose bandings of tribes did not have any lasting power. For the next several centuries many tribes would attempt to join together, but these short-lived alliances would usually fall apart through internal strife and bickering over yurts, horses, women, and grazing rights. During one particularly chaotic episode, the young son of a Mongol chieftain by the name of Temüjin defeated a particularly nasty tribe of Merkits. Impressed with the victory and his control over the army (he forbade looting and raping, pretty much unheard of at the time), a gathering of chieftains gave him the title "Khan" and the control of the tribe. His uncles and cousins however weren't exactly pleased with the throne passing to the young man, and attempted to wrest control of the tribe from him by force. However, in a brilliant military campaign lasting from 1203 - 1205 AD, Temüjin not only destroyed his family rivals but also brought all the remaining tribes under his sway. Never before had one man managed to gain allegiance from all the tribes of Mongols. In 1206, he assumed the title "Genghis Khan", the Universal Ruler. With this monumental event, the Mongolian Empire was officially born. Genghis is primarily well known for his military prowess and conquests, but he only maintained hold of his empire through strict civil discipline and order. He created a code of laws called the Yassa, which governed everyone in the Empire, nobleman and commoner alike. The Yassa imposed harsh penalties on anyone caught not obeying the law (usually death), religious freedom was guaranteed to any and all, all forms of vandalizing was forbidden, and government officials were selected based on merit - not blood. Despite its huge size and disparate groupings of people, the Mongolian Empire was incredibly well-run and one of the safest places on earth, if you followed the rules. Cities caught not following the Khan's decrees were systematically and completely destroyed. Extensive trade routes were set up stretching the length of the empire, allowing safe passage from Europe to China. An efficient mail system called the Yam was also instituted - its structure would later be copied by the US's Pony Express. Roads were built, fair taxes levied, and written language was taught to the Empire's citizens. Life was surprisingly good, provided you obeyed the Khanate. With such an efficient system of government in place, combined with the powerful Mongolian horse archers, country after country fell under the Mongol banner. At the time of Genghis' death in 1227, the Mongolian Empire already stretched from the Pacific to the Caspian Sea - twice the size of even the Roman Empire at its height. His successors continued to subjugate neighboring nations for the next four decades. By 1258 the Mongolian armies had captured Baghdad, killing the caliph after refusal to submit peacefully, thereby opening the door to Syria and the rest of Europe. Some small expeditions were sent as far west as Ukraine and Poland, but the bulk of the army did not pass through Syria. Treaties and letters were sent to the Khan by many of the European nations, hoping for peaceful alliances rather than subjugation. The Mongol's unstoppable expansions may have continued all the way to the Atlantic, but a death in the reigning Khan's family forced the western general and Kublai Khan's son, Hulegu, to withdraw back to Iran. Syria and the new western territories were quickly lost. Hulegu and his cousin Berke (an eastern general) then began fighting in earnest over suspicious deaths in each other's retainers, dividing the internal armies and territories over the dispute. Kublai quickly quashed the internal uprisings and sent the armies back to outward expansion and conquest. However, the solidarity of the Mongolian army and government was weakened, and the foundation for the fall of the Empire was laid. Many internal struggles and squabbles between the Khan's family and its generals ensued for the next hundred years, weakening the empire even further. With the death of the current Khan in 1335, Persia quickly fell to anarchy. The onset of the Black Death at this time also killed most of the government officials, cut off commercial ties with the empire's allies, and killed millions of the populace. Needless to say, chaos erupted. Quickly, the western provinces fell, followed by the loss of China in 1368. The remaining Mongols quickly fled back to their original homeland of Mongolia, breaking into smaller tribes and hordes once again. In thirty short years, the empire that once ruled the world was reduced to rubble. For the next three centuries the Mongols slowly dwindled in power and mostly returned to their tribal ways, with the last Khan dying in 1634. In 1691 the area which encompasses Mongolia today was brought under Chinese rule, where it remained until 1911. Over this time, the nobility's irresponsibility towards their subjects combined with China's unscrupulous taxation practices resulted in rampant poverty throughout the region. With the fall of the Chinese Qing Dynasty in 1911, Mongolia declared its independence, but to little lasting avail. In 1919 it was recaptured by Xu Shuzheng. However, the Russians came to Mongolia's aid and defeated the occupying Chinese three years later. In 1924 and guided by the USSR, the Mongolian People's Republic was born. Life under communist rule was rough. All livestock became owned by the government, Buddhist monasteries and Karakorum were destroyed and their monks slaughtered. Constant wars fought along and inside the country's borders led to much strife for the populace. Poverty became an even worse problem. In 1992, influenced by Mikhail Gorbachev's perestroika campaign in the USSR, Mongolia saw a peaceful democratic revolution, introducing a multi-party system and capitalistic economy in the process. A new constitution was approved and the country was renamed to "Mongolia". The first few years were rocky, but the country has since become an important industrial economy, thanks to its rich mining resources. While still young, Mongolia has formed many positive alliances with world leaders, including Japan, the United States, and China, and is working towards a brighter and more affluent way of life for its people. The Mongolian Empire's mail system (called the Yam) formed the basis for the famed Pony Express. Europe's knowledge of Asia was largely due to the trade routes maintained by the Mongolian Empire.</Text>
	</Row>
	<Row Tag="LOC_PROMOTION_CITY_STATE_COMBAT_DESCRIPTION" Language="en_US">
		<Text>+7 [ICON_Strength] vs. city states.</Text>
	</Row>
	<Row Tag="LOC_PROMOTION_COMBAT_ADJACENT_DESCRIPTION" Language="en_US">
		<Text>+4 [ICON_Strength] for all units adjacent to a Khan.</Text>
	</Row>
  </LocalizedText>
</GameData>
